In 2005, game company id Software open source the engine
2005年，id公司发布了《雷神之锤III：竞技场》的源代码
听写+翻译：SuperBart  原作者Nemean发布于2020-11-29
字幕下载：https://github.com/BenderBolg/Subtitles
该段源代码在 q_math.c 文件里，根据使用改进引擎情况而定
for their video game, Quake III Arena.
In that source code, fans of the game discovered a algorithm
在源代码中，游戏粉丝们找到了一个算法，十分巧妙，很快出名了
that was so ingenious that quickly famous.
And the only thing the algorithm does is calculate the inverse of the square root.
该算法的唯一用途是计算平方根的倒数
If I have to write a piece of code that code calculate the inverse of the square root,
要我写计算平方根倒数的代码的话，我会这么写
this is how I will do it.
Here, I am using the C Programming Language,
此处我用C语言，和《雷神之锤III》的编程语言相同
the same programming language used for the Quake III.
But to be fair, I wouldn't actually write the square root in there myself.
不过说真的，我没有自行实现开平方根的算法
People work more closely with the C language or the CPU design,
那些对C语言底层和CPU设计更熟悉的人们
have already figured out how to calculate the square root.
已经解决了如何用电脑计算平方根的问题了
SuperBart：网上说现在计算平方根是直接调用CPU的浮点运算单元
我翻了GCC版的头文件，<math.h>现在只有一堆宏，<mathcalls.h>的具体实现看不懂
And provided the algorithm to us in a <math.h> file.
并且将该算法写进了<math.h>头文件
And we programmers can then just include in the program.
我们程序员直接将该头文件包含进程序就行了
So what could possibly so interesting about the Quake III's algorithm?
那么，怎么《雷神之锤III》的算法就很有趣了呢？
How did id Software calculate inverse square root?
当时id公司是怎么计算平方根倒数的呢？
At first glance, it doesn't seems to make any scene.
乍看上去，完全解释不通啊
Where does this number 0x5f3759df come from?
这个奇怪的 0x5f3759df 怎么冒出来的？
What does this have to do when taking square root?
算平方根的时候，这步有什么用途？
And why there is a disgusting curse world in the second comment?
为啥注释者在第二个注释那里极致享受了一下？
In this video, I will show you how was
在这期视频，我将会向你展示
some cool bit manipulation you can take in for the square root
计算平方根时候使用到的一些很厉害的位操作
and the algorithm that does this, bears the name, the Fast Inverse Square Root.
以及使用该方法的算法，名称叫平方根倒数速算法
First of all, why does game engine want to calculate
首先，为啥游戏引擎要计算平方根的倒数呢？
the one divided by the square root of x?
If you want implement physics and lighting, or reflections in your game engine,
要在游戏引擎内实现物理效果，光影效果，反射效果的话
it helps when the vector you are calculating with are normalized with the length of 1.
要对使用向量进行单位化，因而我们需要计算平方根倒数
Because other wise, your vector might be too short or too long
要不然的话，向量会过短或过长
and when you do physics with them, things can go wrong.
若在此基础上处理物理效果的话，会出错的
As all of you know, the length of the vector is the
众所周知，向量长度是x^2+y^2+z^2的平方根
square root of the x squared plus y squared plus z squared.
If you don't happen to known this, I claimed you see this in two dimensions.
如果你没反应过来的话，我保证你在二维空间里看到过类似的
It's just the Pythagoras Theorem.
就是勾股定理啊
So if you want to normalize the vector's length to one,
所以，如果你要将向量单位化(把向量长度缩放为1)的话
we want to scale everything down by the length of the vector.
我们要将向量的三个维度都按照模长缩放长度
I mean, obviously, because if we divided the length of the vector
显然，如果我们将向量模长除以向量模长，结果显然为1
by the length of the vector, we obviously get one.
So all the left to do is to divide x, y, and z by the length.
那么，剩下的事情是将x,y,z轴的长度除以向量模长
Or similarly, multiplied by one divided by the length.
或者类似地，乘以向量模长的倒数
You might already see where this is going.
你大概看明白了这其中的问题所在了吧
Calculate the x squared plus y squared plus z squared is easy,
计算x^2+y^2+z^2很简单，更重要的是，真的很快
and more importantly, really fast.
In code, you would implement this: x*x+y*y+z*z.
写代码时，你可以这么写: x*x+y*y+z*z.
And all it did is just three multiplications summed up.
就是三个乘法相加啊
Additions and the multiplications are common operations
加法和乘法是计算机中的基本操作，而且被设计得十分快
and have been designed to be really fast.
The square root, on the other hand, is a terribly slow operations.
然而平方根计算却是十分的慢
And divisions is not much better.
除法计算也快不了哪里去
This is not good if we have several thousands of surfaces,
我们要处理上千的平面，每个向量都要单位化的话，这根本不行啊
where each of the vectors needs to be normalized.
But this also means that in here, we have an opportunity for speed improvements.
但这也意味着，我们有机会可以提高该算法的速度
If we can find, even just the approximation of one divided by the square root of the x,
退一步讲，如果我们可以找到x的平方根倒数的近似结果
as long as it's fast, we can save precious time.
只要算法很快，我们就能节省很多的时间
The Fast Inverse Square Root is such a approximation,
平方根倒数速算法算的就是近似值
with only an error of almost 1%, but been three times as fast.
大约有1%的误差，不过速度是刚才那个的三倍
Looking at the code again, we can see that the beginning is pretty harmless.
再次查看代码，我们可以看到，代码开头基本没啥用
We are given a number called 'number' as input.
我们有一个形参'number'作为输入值
The number where suppose to take the inverse square root off.
我们要计算这个数的平方根倒数
First, with the variable i, we declare 32-bit number.
首先是一个32位整型变量i
Then, we declare two 32-bit decimal numbers, x2 and y.
然后，我们声明两个32位的小数(浮点数)，x2和y
And then we store 1.5 into the variable, with the obvious name, threehalfs.
然后我们将1.5这个数存入一个常量，名称显然对应该数值
注：threehalfs指“二分之三”
Next to the line is simply copy half of it and put it into the x2,
下一行只是很简单地将形参的数值除以2后，存入x2
and the whole then put into the y.
完整的形参则放入y
But it is after that the magic happens.
在此之后，魔法就发生了
Take a moment to look at it again.
再看一下代码
Well, the longer you look at it, the less it make scene.
好吧，你看这个代码时间越长，这代码越解释不通
And that comment on the right aren't really help either.
而代码右面的注释也帮不上什么忙:-P
But they do hit that there are three steps on the algorithm.
但是这至少提醒了我们，这个算法有三步
Puzzling together these three steps, they will show us the brilliancy of this algorithm.
将这三步搞明白，算法就能向我们展示出它的巧妙了
But before we start with these three steps, let's first take a look at binary numbers.
在开始这三步之前，我们先来了解一下二进制数字
They said that in the first line, we declared 32-bit integer.
代码第一行，我们声明了一个32位的整型变量
In the C Programming Language, this is called 'long'.
在C语言中，这被成为'long'
That means we have 32 bits and we can represent numbers with it.
也就是说，我们有32个二进制位，我们可以利用这些位表示数字
But I think you all know how to do with that.
但我觉得，你们肯定知道该如何表示吧
This is one, two, three, four, and so on. Up to around billion.
这是1,2,3,4,以此类推，大约能到几十亿吧
注：2^32 = 42,9496,7296 2^31=21,4748,3648
But in the next line, we declare two decimal numbers. In C, called a float.
而在下一行，我们声明了两个小数，在C中，被称为'float'
注：也就是单精度浮点数
Again, we given 32 bits, and we have to represent the decimal numbers with it.
当然，我们也要用32个二进制位表示小数
How would you do that?
你会怎么表示呢？
If you and I were designing decimal numbers,
如果咱们一起设计小数的话，也许这是我们的设计方案之一
this is probably one way we will do it.
Just put the decimal point in the middle.
直接在中间放小数点就行了啊
In front of the decimal point, we count the usual way.
在小数点之前，我们按照一般方法数出整数部分
One, two, three, four... and so on.
1,2,3,4……以此类推
And after the decimal point, there's no surprise, it is either.
而在小数部分之后，不出所料，也是这样
Just remind yourself, this is binary. So instead of tenth, hundreds, thousands,
不过呢，这可是二进制，所以，我们不数十分位、百分位、千分位
we have halves, fourths, eights, sixteens, and any combinations of them.
我们数二分之一，四分之一，八分之一
十六分之一，以及其所有的组合
Like a halves and a fourths give you three fourths, also known as 0.75.
比如，二分之一加四分之一等于四分之三，也就是0.75
But this idea is actually terrible.
但这个想法实际上很糟糕
We decimate the range the number that can represent.
我们大幅缩小了这些位数可以表示的数字
Before we could represent numbers to around two billion,
之前我们可以表示大约20亿的数字
now only to about 32 thousands.
现在只有3万2千左右了
注：2^16=65536 2^15=32768
Luckily, people much smarter than us
幸亏，那些比我们聪明的人们想出个更好的方法来充分利用这32位
have find a better way to make use of the 32 bits.
They took inspiration from the scientific notation.
他们是从科学记数法中获得的灵感
The same way, we can systematically represent numbers,
这样，我们就能系统地表示数字了
like 23,000 as 2.3 times 10 to the 4.
诸如23000=2.3*10^4
And 0.0034 as 3.4 times 10 to the minus 3.
0.0034=3.4*10^-3
We can also represent them in a binary system.
在二进制体系中，我们也可以这么表示小数
With here for example, 11000(bin) could for an example be 1.1 times 2 to the 4.
举例，二进制数11000可以用1.1*2^4表示
The standard that come up with takes the name IEEE 754.
规定此表示方式的标准称为 IEEE 754
IEEE Standard 754 defines the following:
IEEE 754 标准规定如下：
We are as usual, given 32 bits.
和之前一样，我们有32位
The first bit is a sign bit.
第一位是正负号位
If it's zero, the number is positive.
如果该位是0，则该数为正数
If it's one, the number is negative.
如果该位是1，则该数为负数
But the numbers in Quake III provides the fast inverse square root, are always positive.
但是在游戏中，传给快速平方根倒数函数的值一定是正的
I mean, obviously they are positive.
不用想，这些数绝对是正的啊
If we will have to calculate 1 divided by the square root of -5,
我们要算-5的平方根倒数的话，绝对会出现不好的事情:-P
something definitely is gonna wrong.
So for the rest of this video, we ignore the sign bit, as this is always zero.
所以对于视频的剩余部分，我们不考虑正负号位，默认其为0
Then, the next 8 bits define the exponent.
然后，接下来的8位决定指数部分
That means 2 to the 1, 2 to the 2, 2 to the 3, 2 to the 4, and so on.
也就是2的1次方，2次方，3次方，4次方，以此类推
With 8 bits, we can represent numbers between 0 and 255.
我们可以利用这8位，表示介于0和255之间的数
注：2^8=256 2^7=128 想记住的话，建议玩2048去
But that's not exactly what we need, we also want negative exponent.
但这个仍不是我们想要的，我们还想要负指数
This is why everything is actually shifted down by 127.
这就是为什么这里出现的数用的时候，得减去127
So instead of 2 to the 4, we actually have 2 to the 4 minus 127.
所以说，我们实际得到的是2^(4-127)，而不是2^4
If we actually want exponent to be four, the bits need to be set 131.
如果我们需要的指数必须是4的话，这里必须要被设为131
Because 131-127=4.
因为 131-127=4
The last 23 bits are the mantissa.
剩下的23位表示尾数
As usually in scientific notation, we want to denote one digit.
在科学记数法中，我们要先表示一位整数部分
followed by the comma, followed by the decimal places.
然后是小数点，以及之后的小数部分
But with 23 bits, we can represent numbers from 0 to, but not including, 2 to the 23.
利用这23位，我们能表示从0到2^23(不包括此数)之间的任意一数
Again, that is not exactly what we need.
当然，这还不是我们想要的
For scientific notation, we need an mantissa go to from 1 to 10.
对于十进制科学记数法，我们需要尾数的表示范围在1到10之间
Or in binary scientific notation, to go from 1 to 2.
而在二进制科学记数法中，则是1到2之间
So we can do something that we've already done before.
现在我们可以做一些之前就想做的事情了
Put a comma after the first bit.
在第一位的后面加小数点
This automatically gives us numbers from 1 to 2.
这将会自动地使尾数的范围在1和2之间
But this naive approach is wasteful.
但如此朴素的想法是对位数的浪费
You see, the people that design the standard 754 realize
你看啊，那些设计754标准的人们意识到
that in binary, something happens, that happens in no other base.
在二进制里，会出现一些在其他进制系统里不可能发生的事情
Look at the first digit.
看一下第一位
In scientific notation, the first digit is by definition, always non-zero.
在科学记数法中，第一位按照定义，一定不是0
But in binary, there is only one digit that is not zero-- one!
而在二进制中，只有一个数是非零数，它就是1
And if we know that the first digit will be always be one, there's no need to store it.
要是第一位永远是1的话，我们就没有必要存储它了
Thus, we can save one bit. And moving the comma one digit to the left.
这样，我们节省了一位的存储空间，直接把小数点移动到左面
And fixing an extra one in the number it presents.
然后在回来转换的时候，整数部分改成1即可
Now our mantissa is between one and two.
现在尾数的表示区间是在1和2之间了
Even though the 23 bits gave us numbers between zero and two to the 23.
尽管23位能够表示0到2^23之间的数
We scale them down to get numbers between zero and one.
我们将表示数字的范围缩小到0和1之间
And then we add the extra one, to get numbers between one and two.
然后我们再补一个1，就让其范围为1到2之间
And this already is the main part of the IEEE standard 754.
这就是 IEEE 754 标准的主要内容了
But just, this is so called "normalised numbers".
不过呢，刚才说的都是“规格化数”
The informed viewer known that
懂得多的人知道，这个标准还有非规格化数，非数，无穷和两个零
注：两个零指的是+0和-0
this standard is also included denormalised numbers, NaN numbers,
infinities and two zeroes.
But we won't go into those.
这里我们不会涉猎
Because in Quake III, it just happens that these are never be input into our algorithm.
因为在《雷神之锤III》里，这些数恰巧是不会输入进算法的
Other wise, something definitely has gone wrong anyway.
要不然，绝对会有事情出错的
It is no point should a game engine have to normalize a vector with infinite length.
根本没必要让游戏引擎单位化无限长的向量:-P
For this algorithm, and for the rest of this video,
对于本算法，以及视频的剩下部分
it would be useful to think the mantissa and exponent are binary numbers they are.
思考尾数，指数和二进制数字之间的关系十分有用
If we are given two numbers, one being the mantissa and one being the exponent.
我们有两个数，一个是尾数，一个是指数
23 bits and 8 bits respectively.
分别用23个二进制位和8个二进制位表示
We can get the bit representation with (them).
我们可以利用这些位数表示他们
2 to the 23, times E, plus M, if you think about it.
仔细想的话，是2^23乘以指数E，再加上尾数M
Because multiplying E by 2 to the 23 just shift E by 23 digit.
因为将指数E乘以2^23，相当于将其进23个二进制位
So that's how one could write the bits.
所以，我们可以用这些二进制位表示浮点数了
But we get the actual number behind the bits with this formula.
我们可以用这个公式算数这些位数表示的实际数字
This should seems familiar to you.
你应该很熟悉这个公式了
SuperBart：除非你退出视频，或者上政治课睡着了/滑稽
Here we have the exponent with 127 subtracted from it.
这里，我们的指数被减去了127
And here we have the mantissa, with an extra one in front.
我们的尾数前面也多了一个1
But now, something completely different.
不过，现在的事情有点不同了
For no obvious reason at all, let's take the logarithm out of that expression.
这里，我们将完全没有缘由地对该公式取对数
Since we're doing computer science here, we take the logarithm base two.
既然我们干的是计科的事情，我们对数的底数取为2
We simplify as much we can.
我们这里尽量简化
Take out the exponent.
将指数取出
But then, we get stuck.
然后，我们卡住了:-(
But not so the creators of Quake.
然而《雷神之锤》的开发者并没有
Developer Gary Tarolli knew the trick to get the rid of the logarithm.
开发者 Gary Tarolli 知道去掉(简化)对数的技巧
注：就现在所知，平方根倒数速算法最早由Gary Tarolli在SGI Indigo的开发中使用
You see, the trick is the approximation to log of 1 plus x.
技巧就是log(1+x)的极限
For small value of x, log of 1 plus x is approximately equal to x.
对于很小的x，log(1+x)大致相当于x
If you think about it, this approximation is actually correct.
仔细想的话，这个近似实际上是正确的
注：已知ln(1+x)~x，又loga(1+x)=ln(1+x)/lna，所以.......
For x equals 0, and x equals 1.
如果x=0，然后x=1的话，(就和原函数的对应因变量完全相同)
But we add additional term, μ(mu would be written as follow).
但如果我们再加入一个校正系数，称为μ
This correction term can be chosen freely.
该校正系数可任意选择
Again, with mu equals to 0, this approximation is correct at 0 and 1.
若校正系数μ为0，该近似函数将于0和1处与原函数所得因变量相同
But it turns out that set mu in this number,
不过最终得出结论，将校正系数μ设为该值
gives the smallest error on average, for numbers between 0 and 1.
在0到1的范围内，总体偏差最小
So going back to our formula, we apply our tricks.
回到公式，我们利用这个技巧
As M divided by 2 to the 23, it is indeed a value between 0 and 1.
由于M已经被2^23除去，它一定是0到1之间的数
We rearrange a little bit more and we finally see why we did all those calculations.
再稍微整理一下，我们终于知道为啥我们要如此计算了
M plus E time 2 to the 23 appears.
指数E乘以2的23次方，再加上尾数M
That's our bits representation.
这就是浮点数的二进制表示嘛
So let's think about we just said,
接下来，我们再想想我们之前干了啥
We apply the logarithm to our formula, and got the bit representation.
我们把公式取了对数，得到了二进制表示的形式
Just scaled and shifted by some constants.
仅仅是缩放了一下，移动了几位
So in some sense, the bit representation of a number is its own logarithm.
在某种意义上，浮点数的二进制表示的就是它的对数形式
Armed with this knowledge, we can finally start
懂了这么多，我们终于可以开始了解快速平方根倒数算法的三部曲了
with the three steps of the Fast Inverse Square Root.
The first step is actually not complicated.
第一步实际上并不复杂
It's just looks complicated because of the memory address trickery.
看起来很复杂，是因为对这行代码是在内存地址方面做了些手脚
So we store our number into y, and now we want to do cool bit manipulation tricks.
我们将数字存入y，然后我们想做些很厉害的位操作
Floats, unfortunately, don't come with a tool which we need to do bit manipulation.
然而呢，浮点数没有做位操作的方法
The reason you cannot do bit manipulation on floats,
为啥浮点数不能做位操作呢，因为它根本就不是为位操作设计的啊
is that they were never designed to do so.
Floats are inherently tied to IEEE standard 754.
浮点数本质上严格遵守IEEE 754标准
Longs, on the other hand, were designed to do bits manipulations on them.
然而，长整型数可以用来做位操作
For example, here's one tricks.
此处用一个小技巧举例
Bits shifting along to the left, doubles it.
向左位平移能将这个数加倍
And bits then shifting to the right, halves it.
向右位平移能将这个数减半
And yes, if your numbers are odd, you would end up rounding.
当然，如果是个奇数的话，最终会有舍去
SuperBart：抱歉各位，odd(奇数)和even(偶数)搞反了……
But hey, we're willing to accept such inaccuracy,
不过呢，我们可以接受这点不准确，只要这个算法够快就好
as long as it means that this algorithm is fast.
C, as pretty much all other programming languages do,
像其他的编程语言一样，C语言提供了一种方法
provides a way to converts from a float to a long.
能将浮点数转换为长整型数
This conversion does what most programmers needed to do.
这种转换能满足程序员的大部分需要
namely convert from a decimal number to an ordinary integer as best it can do.
就是将一个小数(浮点数)尽力转换为一个整型数
So if we can get a float, like 3.33, it converse to an integer, in this case, 3.
如果浮点数是3.33的话，它能将其转换成整型数，也就是3
But this is not the conversion we need here.
不过这个转换不是我们想要的
First of all, we don't care about the result in integer number.
首先，我们对转换后的整型结果不感兴趣
We want to somehow, keep our float.
我们想让其保持浮点数的形式
And secondly, the bits that are lie behind numbers are messed up.
其次，浮点数背后的那堆二进制数也都被打乱了
We don't want this conversion to mess with this bits.
我们不希望转换对二进制位有任何影响
The only thing we want to do is to put the bits, one to one, into a long.
我们想要的是，逐位将其转换到长整型形式
The way you achieve this, is to convert the memory address, not the number.
你要这么干的话，就要转换该数对应的内存地址，而不是数字本身
First, we get the address of y, this is the address of the float.
首先，我们得到了浮点数y的地址，这个是一个float类型的地址
Then you convert the address from a float address into a long address.
然后我们将该地址转换成long(长整型)类型的地址
The address itself doesn't change, but C now thinks
地址本身没变，但是C语言认为该地址内的数是个长整型了
the number living at the address is now a long.
So then, you read what's written at that address.
然后就该读取该地址内的数字了
Because C now think that this is a address of a long,
由于现在C语言认为该地址的类型是long
it will read the number at the address, as it were a long.
它将按照长整型类型读取该地址里的数字
Like this, we tricked C by lifting the conversion away from the number itself
像这样，我们避开数字本身，利用该数所在的地址
to the address of the number.
运用了C语言的一些手段实现目的
And that's how we get the bits of the number into i.
这样该浮点数的二进制表示存入了i
I donno know what else to say, that's just how C works,
没啥可说的，C语言就是这样工作的啊
so let's just go to the next step.
我们直接进入下一步
The intuition behind the second step is the following.
算法的第二步有一点很显然
Remind yourself, bit shifting a number to the left doubles it.
还记得吗，向左位平移能将这个数加倍
And shifting to the right, halves it.
向右位平移能将这个数减半
But what would happen if we did something like this to an exponent？
但要对于指数进行该变换，会发生什么呢
Doubling an exponent squares the number,
指数加倍，相当于对该数平方
and halving the exponent gives us an square root.
指数减半，相当于对该数进行开方
But now also negating the exponent, give us 1 divided by the square root of x.
现在对指数取负，就是将x开方后取倒数
This is exactly what we need.
这正是我们想要的
So let's remind ourselves what our goals is here.
所以，我们要明白我们的目标就是这个
We have our numbers stored into y,
我们的数字存于y
and our goal was to calculate the 1 divided by the square root of y.
我们的目标就是计算y的平方根倒数
As our already said, calculate this directly is too hard and too expensive.
之前提到，直接计算相当困难，耗时很久
But we extracted the bits from y.
但是我们已经提取出y的二进制位表示
And we have seen with the IEEE standard 754,
我们也知道按照IEEE 754标准
that the bits of the number are, in some sense, its own logarithm.
浮点数的二进制表示在某种意义上，就是该二进制数的对数
That means, in i, we have stored the log of y, up to some scaling and shifting.
也就是说，在i里，我们存有y的对数，当然还有一些放缩和变换
I claim that the problem will become way easier if we work with log.
我觉得要是处理对数的话，问题会变得简单
Instead of trying so hard to calculate the 1 divided by the square root of y,
与其花很多力气直接计算y的平方根倒数
we instead calculate log of 1 divided by the square root of y.
我们直接计算y平方根倒数的对数
We rewrite this to log of y to the power of minus half.
这里重新写成y的负二分之一次方的对数
So we can take the exponent.
这样指数可以提到前面
Calculate this is stupidly easy.
算这个可就简单多了
You might think "Oh no! We have a division in here.
你也许会想:"天哪，这里可有除法。刚开始不是说除法很慢的吗?"
Didn't you said that in the beginning, that division are slow?"
Oh yes, but remember that we can do bit shifts now.
没错，不过这里我们可以进行位平移了
Instead of dividing by 2, we just bit shift once to the right.
我们不算除以2，我们直接将其向右平移一位
This already explains why we do minus i, bit shift once to the right.
这就解释了为啥我们要算i的负数，并将i向右移动一位
But why this number 0x5f3759df here again?
不过，0x5f3759df这个数在这里有啥用啊?
Well, because our algorithm is actually scales and shifts it.
根据公式，我们还要放缩和位平移
So let's calculate it and understand where it comes from.
我们来算一下这个数是从哪里来的
Let Γ (gamma would be written at below) be our solution.
设Γ为解，则解Γ和y对数的负二分之一方相同
Then we knew, the log of gamma equals to the log of y to the power of minus half,
which equals to minus half times log of y.
也就是y的对数乘以负二分之一
Now we replace the logarithm with the bit representation.
现在，我们将该对数用二进制位来表示
And then we just solve for the bits of gamma.
接下来，我们仅需算出解Γ的二进制位表示
I spared the details but this is the result.
此处略去细节，结果如下
The magic number turns out, to be the remnants of the error in terms of mu,
那个魔力数字，原来是按照校正系数μ
the scaling factor and the shifting.
放缩系数和平移系数来纠正误差的
Now we have the bits of the solution
现在我们有结果的位表示了
and we can just reverse this step from the evil hack
我们仅需再按照邪恶的位操作，将二进制位转换回浮点数结果即可
to get back to the actual solution from those bits.
Well... actually, that isn't exact solution, just an approximation.
实际上，这不是确切结果，仅仅是一个近似值
This is why we need the third step.
这就是为啥我们需要第三步了
After the previous step, we have a pretty decent approximation.
上一步之后，我们得到了一个还可以的的近似值了
But we did pick up some error terms here and there.
但我们的结果或多或少有一些误差
But thanks to Newton's Method, we can make
但按照牛顿迭代法，我们可以把还可以的近似值变成很好的近似值
the really good approximation out of the decent one.
Newton's Method is a technique that find the root of a given function.
牛顿迭代法是一个用来寻找方程根的方法
Meaning it finds a x, for which f(x) equals zero.
也就是找到一个x，使f(x)=0
It does so by taking a approximation that returning a better approximation.
它的实现方法是，通过取近似的方式来得到一个更好的近似
Usually, you repeat this process until you close enough to the actual solution.
通常，你可以重复该过程，直到与实际结果十分接近
But it turns out that here we are already close enough to the actual solution.
然而实际上，我们已经很接近实际结果了
that one iteration suffices to get an error of 1 percent.
一次迭代得到的结果，会有1%的误差
The only things Newton's Method needs is the function and its derivative.
牛顿迭代法仅需两件东西，方程对应函数和函数的导数
And what Newton's Method does is that it takes a x value,
牛顿迭代法呢，首先取一个x值
and it tries to guess by how much it is off from being the roots.
然后通过计算f(x)以及其导数来估计该值与实际根的偏差
It does so by calculating f(x) and its derivative.
We can write f(x) as a y, and the derivative as dy over dx.
我们将f(x)写为y，导数则是dy/dx
We have the ratio between y and x offset, and y itself.
我们得到了y的偏差和x的偏差，以及y本身
So to get the x offset, we just divide y by the ratio.
要得到x偏差，我们仅需将y除以其导数
So then we simply subtract the offset to get the new x.
然后我们减去偏差，得到一个新x
The informed viewer can now verify that the last line is
某些学霸们现在可意识到最后一行就是按照公式实现的牛顿迭代法
Newton Iteration that apply to the function.
f(y) equals to 1 divided by the y squared minus x.
f(y)等于y平方的倒数减去x
Notice that the y being the root of the function
注意，作为方程根的y与x的平方根倒数是相同的
is equivalent to y being in the inverse square root of x.
I really encourage you to verify the last line of the code.
我强烈建议大家自行验证该代码的最后一行
Since it is really surprising that even though both the function
因为尽管该公式以及牛顿迭代法本身有除法，但是代码里没有
and Newton's Method have division in them, the code does not.
Which means the algorithm is, and stays stays fast.
意味着该算法一直会很很高速地运行
Now we finally understand the Fast Inverse Square Root.
现在我们终于搞明白快速平方根倒数算法了
It only took us the knowledge of IEEE 754,
仅仅是利用到了了 IEEE 754 标准知识
an trick to outsmart the C Programming Language,
对C语言特性的灵活利用
magic bits operations,
具有魔力的位平移
and the calculates behind the Newton's Method.
以及牛顿迭代法背后的运算法则
注：ioquake改进版中，引入了一个联合
typedef union floatint_u \floatint_t;
这样，第一步可以不用更改指针类型了
不过我很怀疑有多少人会看到这里......